<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meditations for the passion weeke following the order of the time and story. / By N. Taylour..</title>
            <author>Taylour, N. (Nathanael).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23857.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S95495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532449</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180876</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00785)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180876)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2142:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meditations for the passion weeke following the order of the time and story. / By N. Taylour..</title>
                  <author>Taylour, N. (Nathanael).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 195, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Printers to the Vniversity of Cambridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXVII [1627].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initial.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]³ A-H¹² I².</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180876:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEDITATIONS for the Paſſion Weeke Following the order of the Time and Story.</p>
            <p>By N. TAYLOVR.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Pet. 2.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that yee ſhould follow his ſteps</p>
               <p>Who his owne ſelfe bare our ſinnes in his owne body on the Tree, that Wee beeing dead to ſinnes, ſhould live unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, by whoſe ſtripes ye were healed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed by the Printers to the <hi>Vniverſity</hi> of CAMBRIDGE. MDCXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:180876:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:180876:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſh. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. MAW Maſter of Trinitie Colledge <hi>in Cambridge.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right worthy and Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have no better way to ſhew my thankefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of your love and care over me, then by ſending you my thoughts, that is, a fewe of my better Meditations, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for mine owne uſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not worthy your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: yet ſuch as they are, I hope they will finde the ſame favour with you, that my ſelfe have done: which though it bee too much for me to expect, yet I can hope for no leſſe, in regard of the gentleneſſe of your nature, and
<pb facs="tcp:180876:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>forwardnes to reſpect me, before I had time to deſerve of you. The thing I aimed at in them, was to make the Storie they belong to, as orderly, as it is perfect: ſo that if they have no other uſe, they may ſtand in ſtead of an harmony to right any doubt about our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours ſufferings. As for Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which I deſired to ſtirre up in my ſelfe and others by them, it could not bee beſtowed upon a better ſubject: howbeit, if ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the beſt I have fail'd, or my affections want heate of zeale; I hope nevertheles, that my ſparke may kindle a greater fire, where it findes ſewell, by the light of which, many may both ſee, and bee warmed. And now I have brought my worke to the fire, you may doe to it as you pleaſe; for I put it into your hands, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:180876:4"/>pardon for my boldnes, and ſo ending, with my daily pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for your daily encreaſe in all things that may make you an happie Governour of the Society you are in, or may riſe to.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all dutie, <hi>NATH. TAYLOVR.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180876:4"/>
            <head>¶ Meditations for SUNDAY, <hi>Beeing the firſt day in the</hi> weeke, by the Iewes <hi>account.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Verie Day hath his Night, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer his Winter, every Spring his Fall, and every Life his Death: And as ſome Nights are darker then other, ſome Autumnes more unſeaſonable, ſome Winters more ſharpe; ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180876:5"/>are ſome Deaths more, yea much more cruell then other be: Some men fall like fruite, other are cut downe like trees; ſome are pluckt up in the flower, other by the roote; that is, ſome men <hi>die onely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suet. Aug.</hi> Non aliter quàm ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plics morte puntit.</note> other with tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is two, or more deaths in one. Yet one thing, nevertheleſſe, this diverſitie findes to agree in, That all men die with paine: for two ſuch friends as the ſoule and bodie are, cannot be parted without grieving: or, to ſpeake more to the quicke, Two, which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180876:5"/>nay GOD himſelfe once joyned together to make but one Perſon, cannot be ſevered again without cutting: neither is it an ordinary paine that divides theſe two, but ſuch an one as can but once be ſuffered, and hath a name by it ſelfe, as it hath alſo a nature different from other paines; for we call it, <hi>The Pang of Death:</hi> which paine though we cannot learne what bounds it hath, becauſe it is a pain that comes not to his height till wee be paſt telling where it holds us:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180876:6"/>yet can wee eaſily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne, that it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in every man: for the ſtrugling in ſome, and the quietnes in other, ſhew either the paine to be more, or the patience leſſe: and yet a ſtrong patience will often out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare a grievous extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, with little appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of griefe: ſo that this Fit hath many mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes in it, if any one could come againe, like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to tel us them.</p>
            <p>But among all Deaths, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whatſoever they bee, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was any ſo ſtrange as our Saviours was: for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180876:6"/>in it, both paine and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience met in their extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: ſo that paine did her worſt to overcome patience, and patience her beſt to overcome paine; and yet neither paine had the upper hand, though it killed, nor patience loſt though <hi>Chriſt</hi> died: becauſe he that ſuffered, ſuffered but at his owne will, and his ſuffering beſides was the paine of Paine; yea, the death of Death it ſelfe: yet howſoever it prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not, ſo great never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles was this Paſſion, &amp; ſo grievous, as it hath nor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180876:7"/>can have, none to ſample it: for <hi>Chriſts</hi> paine was ſuch as never Creature felt, neither can doe: and on the other ſide, his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſo great, as for all the ſorrow hee ſuffered on the Croſſe, he is not read to have uttered a groane there. So that it may be eaſily diſcerned, that Patience had the victorie: becauſe paine could neither make her leave the field till ſhee liſt, nor bring her to any conditions but her own, which were moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</p>
            <p>This is but one occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:180876:7"/>but the Death I have named, containes (further) a Story, that may take up <hi>(Reader)</hi> thy whole intention: for in it thou ſhalt ſee (wonder at it) a Croſſe ſet up to crucifie GOD on, Life condemned to die, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to ſuffer: and, which is more, all this effected, yet nothing done to advance the contrarie partie: for through <hi>Chriſts</hi> Bodie, Death ſlew it ſelfe, and Sinne and Satan tooke their deadly wounds. See againe (and againe wonder at it) Patience
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180876:8"/>exalted upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her Throne the Croſſe, and crowned with Thorne, whereof every point is deadly; yet ſtill unmooved, and like her Selfe. And as thou readſt theſe things, written with blood in ſtead of inke upon the wide-open Booke of the Croſſe, if thou apply them to thy ſelfe, and weigh them in thy heart as <hi>Marie</hi> did, they were for thee all ſuffered, and <hi>Chriſts</hi> victorie is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thy hope of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, his Croſſe is thy Crowne, his ſuffering thy ſalvation, his death thy life.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:180876:8"/>
            <p> Here is now a Booke, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> written in red letters, laid open for thee to reade on, I meane the Croſſe: and every word in it muſt be read two wayes, as having a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and contrary ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. When thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneſt to reade, everie thing ſignifies as thou ſeeſt it written: but when thou commeſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue them, they meane quite otherwiſe. For at firſt, thou ſhalt ſee ſcorn, ſhame, ſuffering, death, and all theſe laid upon Innocencie for thy Sin: but this when thou haſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180876:9"/>acknowledged, thou muſt reade every word contrarie over againe: ſo that then, ſhame is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſuffering is victorie, death is life, both to him that bore them, and to thee that beleeveſt. And now thou haſt the ſecret of this ſtrange Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, ply thy book hard, and take out of it as much as thou canſt for thy learning: eſpecially this weeke thou muſt do it, becauſe this is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie time, in which theſe things were firſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, not with inke (as I ſaid) but with his blood
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180876:9"/>that died for thee. Reade then, and learne, and meditate, and apply: which all thou maiſt do though thou bee no ſcholler; for he that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw booke before, may knowe his <hi>Chriſt-Croſſe,</hi> though hee can reade no other letter. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
            </p>
            <p>When thou heareſt mee thus ſpeake of a Croſſe, and ſuffering, thou canſt looke for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in ſuch a booke but Tragicall: and ſo it is a Tragedy, even the wofulleſt argument that ever was acted. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in it are all great
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180876:10"/>men, as in Tragedies: <hi>Herod</hi> a King, <hi>Pilate</hi> the Romane Deputie, the Rulers of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the chiefe Phariſies, the High Prieſts: all High, thou ſeeſt, yea the moſt High himſelfe, for GOD hath a part in it. The <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or firſt part, containes the Life of Death, that is, the furie of <hi>Chriſts</hi> enemies: the <hi>Epitaſis</hi> or ſecond, the Death of Life, that is, of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is Life in the fountaine, even <hi>The Life:</hi> the <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> or laſt part in it, is the Death of Death, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180876:10"/>by <hi>Chriſt</hi> his dying was utterly deſtroyed, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of efficacie to hurt any of thoſe that belong unto GOD any more. The beginning of this Tragedie (as it falls to be) is joyous, but the end was bitter. The firſt Scene of it, was <hi>Chriſts</hi> riding, as upon this day, into <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. The bravery of this ſhow was not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and yet it is a wonder to ſee how it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the multitude:<note place="margin">Chriſt hath enough fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers when he comes ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph; but &amp;c.</note> the whole Citie was moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: Men, and Trees too, ſtript the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to ſtrow
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180876:11"/>the way as hee went: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mouth was full of <hi>Hoſanna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>That is,</hi> Heare us O Lord.</note> even the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens alſo: and if they had held their peace, the very ſtones would have ſpoken. And who would have thought, when he ſawe and heard theſe things, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould have needed to have wept over this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or theſe ſhould have bin the men that ſhould betray him? But follow on thy Saviour into the Citie, and thou ſhalt ſee what entertainement he finds there, not for his owne, for he had none;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180876:11"/>but for thy ſinnes, that thou maiſt learne to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile them. For,</p>
            <p>When thou commeſt into the City, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> thou ſhalt ſee the multitude indeed follow <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but it is the multitude, even the variable unconſtant mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: ſo that among ſo many followers of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> onely his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were his true fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. Thou ſhalt ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, while the Citie is mooved with joy, the Phariſies on the other ſide as much mooved with anger, and asking even our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180876:12"/>of the Children which cryed <hi>Hoſanna, Heareſt thou what theſe ſay?</hi> When thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into the Temple, thou ſhalt ſee the houſe of his glory, which hee had choſen of old to put his Name there, filled with buyers and ſellers, whom there is no way to drive out, but with a whippe. Therefore hee makes one, and burning in zeale, reſts not till hee have driven out all theſe ungodly prophaners out of his Sanctuary, throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe their tables, and overthrowing their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180876:12"/>ſeates, and not ſuffering ſo much as a veſſell to be carried through the Temple: neither had they all any power to reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe things are written for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> for the ill is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that we may learne to avoide it, the good that we may imitate it: But cheifly muſt our eye be bent on our Saviours actions in this ſtory, for that is the beſt copy we have to follow. Follow him then as he rides, and ſee his humility: It is but an aſſe that he ſits on, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180876:13"/>thou maiſt follow him the better: yet is he that is thus meanly ſeated, the King not only of <hi>Zion,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> calls him,<note place="margin">Zach. <hi>9.9.</hi>
               </note> but of Heaven &amp; Earth: This thou maiſt learne, even of the children that follow him; for their cry is <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> that is, <hi>Heare us O Lord:</hi> and againe they ſay, <hi>Bleſſed bee the King that commeth in the Name of the Lord:</hi> Take thou up this cry together with them, elſe thou muſt not ioyne with this company: for from the aged to the children, all had theſe two voices in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180876:13"/>their mouth, <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bleſſed be the King.</hi> The one is the voice of praier, the other of praiſe: two workes that peculiarly belong to this Day, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, which is <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt other things, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>S. Iohn</hi> tells us of certaine <hi>Greekes, Proſelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.20.</note> that comming to worſhip at the Feaſt, deſired as this day to ſee <hi>Ieſus:</hi> neither doth he put them backe, but upon this occaſion, as it ſeemes, begins to ſpeake of his ſuffering which was to follow ere many daies were over. Be thou aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180876:14"/>that any ſtrangers ſhould preſſe neerer to heare, or ſee him then thou: and be not afraid hee will reject thee, if thy deſire bee to learne; for he does not ſo unto theſe. Eſpecially take heede thou beeſt not left out, when he goes into the Temple: for by his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in that Temple, thou maiſt learne how to behave thy ſelfe in the Temple of thy Body: that as he with a whip of ſmal cords, whipped the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſellers out of the Temple, overthrew alſo the tables of the money<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changers, and the ſeats of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180876:14"/>them that ſold Doves; ſo muſt we make us a whipp of cords, the ſmaller the better, and whip out of the Temple and Citie too our corrupt affections; neither let them ſo much as once looke againe into the Sanctuarie of our Soules, no not though they come to ſell Doves for ſacrifice, or would change our money into gold. At leaſt, let them never have power to ſell our Soules, which onely <hi>Chriſt</hi> was able to buy: but let us throwe downe their tables, overthrowe their ſeats, ſcatter their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:180876:15"/>merchandize, and not ſuffer any veſſell that is not hallowed to come through our thoughts. Thus ſhall wee bee fit to ſanctifie this Day, when wee have thus hallowed our harts anew by clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them: otherwiſe, we ſhall juſtly heare the ſame which was ſpoken to theſe prophaners, <hi>My Houſe ſhall bee called a houſe of Prayer, but yee have made it a Denne of Theeves.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:180876:15"/>
            <head>Meditations for MONDAY.</head>
            <p>FRom <hi>Bethany</hi> comes our Holy Lord this Morning to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; from his friends that had entertained him, to his enemies that would crucifie him; and that to ſave them, if they would have beene ſaved. This was the towne of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> and <hi>Marie,</hi> whome <hi>Chriſt</hi> loved: therefore hee honoured it with a miracle, in raiſing up <hi>Lazarus</hi> their Brother,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180876:16"/>and with making it his retyring place. And well it was, howſoever, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had any place to retire to ſo neere <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> howbeit his own Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie owed him a better, if it had done him right: yet for all that, he muſt go to <hi>Bethanie</hi> to ſeek his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, if he will have one, and pay deare for it too: for he ſatisfied his Hoſt to the full, both for his coſt, and curteſie, in that hee raiſed him out of his grave, after he had lyen in it foure dayes. It goes hard with our Saviour (mee thinkes) when hee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180876:16"/>muſt bee glad to raiſe his hoſt out of his grave: yet it is well that hee found one, though hee opened the earth for him. For a man may digge in many places, and not find gold; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> may often call at the graves of Mankind buried in Sinne, and find never a <hi>Lazarus</hi> to heare him. Holy <hi>Lazarus!</hi> thou couldſt heare <hi>Chriſt</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wert dead; but well are wee if wee can heare him while wee are alive: yet this we may doe if we will, and now is the time; for this Weeke <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath many things to ſay,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:180876:17"/>that concerne our ſoules health: yea, words he hath to ſpeake, which may put Life into thee, if thou wert dead, ſo thy heart be fit, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> his houſe was, to receive him: only drawe neere, and bring thy Will with thee, and thou ſhalt heare him.</p>
            <p>By this time <hi>Chriſt</hi> is on his way comming to <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> &amp; by the way, as he comes, he is an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred: (he was no glutton then, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> accuſed him) and eſpying a Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree a farre off, he goes to it, yet not to ſatisfie hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; for the time of figges
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:180876:17"/>was not yet come; but to give us a Leſſon, how he hates ſpiritual unfruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. When he came to it therefore, and ſawe no figges, though by the yeare time it ſhould have beene ſo, hee curſed the Tree, and anon it withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. If this bee done to the greene Tree, (for <hi>S. Marke</hi> hath noted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.13.</note> that it had leafes, though it had no fruite) what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us, the dry and wild one? And if <hi>Chriſt</hi> require figges of it before the time, may he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire fruit of us whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he comes, yea gather
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180876:18"/>where he ſcattered not? yet let no man accuſe him of injuſtice: for he ſowed once, but we let it be roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up; he ſcattered once, but we let the Enemie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it: that is, hee gave grace to Man, before the Fall, that would ever have been bearing fruit; and to the trees, a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Autumne for our ſakes; therefore he might call on the Fig-tree in Winter, and not bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; and may looke for good workes of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, ere they receive Grace: but much more may he of us, who boaſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180876:18"/>to have the life of Grace in us. Feare then, and faile not to bring foorth thy fruite in his ſeaſon, and GOD can, and will put difference betweene thee &amp; a Fig-tree. He ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not for Oxen, and it is no great matter if a fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree wither: but his ſight is better then to ſee men walking like Trees; hee will ſpare thee therefore, and give thee an example out of them: onely thou muſt not bee a ſtocke, or barren wood, but thy fruite muſt appeare in his due time. This uſe thou maiſt make of this ſtorie.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180876:19"/>Howbeit our Saviour makes another himſelfe; namely, by example of his owne faith, which had ſo ſoone wrought this miracle, to ſtirre up Faith in his Diſciples, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in prayer. But this belongs to the next day.</p>
            <p>What our Saviour taught this day in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the Evangeliſts have not recorded. <hi>S. Marke</hi> ſets downe the Storie of our Saviours whipping the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple, as if it had happened this day: either becauſe they were ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180876:19"/>as to come into the Temple this day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſo our Lord was enforced to renewe the action: or elſe it is the ſame that the other Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts ſpeake of, but (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtome elſewhere obſerved in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ) order is not ſtrictly kept in the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of time. For the Holy Ghoſt meant to deliver a rule for Faith, rather then for Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie. And yet we ſhould not have wanted that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but that, partly, GOD would ſometime leave order unexpreſt, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:180876:20"/>our diſorder towards him: partly, becauſe hee would try our Faith, whether wee would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him on his Word, or condemne him when wee ſaw the leaſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of contrarietie. Appearance, I ſay, for ſo it is only: neither is there any diſſidence in matter, or circumſtance, in any place of Scripture, but it may be reconciled.</p>
            <p>Well then: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> This daies Sermon is not printed; yet that our Saviour taught this day, I take it to bee evident: for <hi>S. Luke</hi> reports, that hee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180876:20"/>taught daily in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Alſo his prolixe, and continued Parables, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered on other dayes, make it credible, that he would not be ſilent upon this. Yet this one dayes labour amongſt other we have not, becauſe he hath left us ſufficient for our ſoules health in that we have; ſo that we need not looke for more. Alſo, the leſſe we have, the leſſe wee have to learne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the want of that wee have not, may ſtirre up our affection to that wee have. If thou have but a little ground and a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:180876:21"/>little ſeed, till it the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for thou haſt better leiſure, and it may yeeld thee an hundred for one: howſoever, it cannot but yeeld thee more, then all the great field of the ſluggard. <hi>If all that Chriſt ſpoke &amp; did were written, I ſuppoſe,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Divine (or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>the world could not containe the bookes that ſhould be written.</hi> His meaning is, either to ſhew <hi>Chriſts</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in teaching, which was ſuch as would have wearied the hands of all writers to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:180876:21"/>have followed him: or elſe, if all that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpoke had beene writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the Comments upon his Text would have been numberleſſe. Either of theſe are eaſie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; for we ſee daily that the tongue of the teacher goes ſo quicke, as no hand can follow it, but by Brachygraphie; &amp; the Comments upon our Saviours words that we have, are ſo many, as the world is already full of them: ſo many Comments there be, ſo many Volumes, ſo many Treatiſes, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180876:22"/>more then a mans life to read them all, as they ſhould be. Be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent then, and praiſe GOD for that which thou haſt, read it, lay it to thy heart, and meditate how thou maiſt practiſe it; for that thou learneſt of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is never truly thy owne, till thou bring it into practiſe: and thus thou maiſt heere under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaning of that Proverbe, that ſayes, <hi>No knowledge is like that, which a man hath at his fingers ends,</hi> that is, which he hath ready for practiſe.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:180876:22"/>
            <p> Now that this Day is done, if thou wilt walke backe with thy Lord againe to <hi>Bethanie,</hi> thou ſhalt doe more then we read the whole multitude did yeſterday, that were at firſt ſo dutifull about him. That he lodged this Night againe in that little village, it appeares (as I take it) by the Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, which he curſed as he came by it to day, and to morrow paſſes by againe, and ſpeakes of what had happened to it, as will appeare better out of the next dayes ſtory. Well then: if
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180876:23"/>thou wilt follow thy Maſter thither, the jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is but ſhort; ſome fifteene furlongs as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, or there about. If thou doubt to want lodging, becauſe the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage is little, yet hope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe it is hoſpital: or if thou ſhouldeſt watch one Night with thy Saviour, or about him, thou ſhouldeſt not looſe thy labour, and ſo it would be worth thy paines alſo. For who would not want one Nights ſleepe to be ſo neere <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to heare his laſt words, &amp; ſee his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180876:23"/>laſt actions; which as they were alwaies graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo now certainly were moſt affectionate: for it is the Nature of Love, to ſhew it ſelfe moſt loving, when it is a leaving. So have I ſeene two friends, that having kept their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance till they were to part, yet then could hold no longer, but burſt out and wept, of meere affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>If thou aske how thou ſhouldſt get ſo neere thy Saviour, as toſee, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> and heare him; I anſwer, draw neere unto him by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:180876:24"/>Prayer, by Faſting, by Thankfulnes, by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; meditate of him all the day long, and of the price, and Love of his Paſſion: and, when thou haſt done thus on the Day time, at Night lay the ſame thoughts under thy pillow, and reſt upon them, or rather upon him, ſleeping, and waking. Thus ſhalt thou both follow him to his lodging, and Inne with him too. And if thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt this every Night, thou doeſt but thy duty; for this is a weeke that ſhould thriftily be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:180876:24"/>into houres and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, by hearing, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, prayer, or meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which at Night ſhould be laid up within thee to digeſt, and ere the Morning they will be a part of thee, as thy nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment is. And one thing let us obſerve to this purpoſe ere we leave this Day, That the matter which <hi>Chriſt</hi> uttered this day was not written, that wee might have one day, at leaſt, in this weeke, free for meditation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:180876:25"/>
            <head>Meditations for TUESDAY.</head>
            <p>RIſe up with thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (O my ſoule) and put on him for thy garments, that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt follow backe this morning to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Cleave to him alſo as he goes, and liſten what he ſayes; for this is a day, in which the double doore of his lips is open, to poure forth the treaſure of his heart; even the riches of his wiſdome, and mercy, unto thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:180876:25"/>that have eares and hearts to receive them: for this day he not only teaches his owne, but puts his enemies to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, by the evidence of his wiſdome, and utterly convinces them. His Diſciples give him the firſt occaſion of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by ſhewing him the fig-tree, which he had curſed yeſterday, this Morning withered up by the rootes; which whileſt they beheld with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they are bold to make him alſo acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with in theſe words, <hi>How ſoone is the fig-tree
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:180876:26"/>withered?</hi> A marvaile was this, nay a miracle too, and that in this tree above other Trees: for the fig-tree is call'd <hi>Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens arbor,</hi> that is, the wiſe tree, becauſe it never puts out till the Spring be confirm'd, &amp; Winter utterly over; therefore of all trees it is leaſt ſubject to blaſting.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 9.11.</note> For this cauſe (among other) the figtree in the booke of <hi>Iudges</hi> (it may be) is put among thoſe wiſe trees that refuſe the Kingdome over the other. But there is no wiſdome, nor underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nor counſell againſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:180876:26"/>the Lord: if <hi>Chriſt</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, the poore fig-tree muſt wither, have it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo well provided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt weather, in his late, and deliberate bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. This is the very uſe that our Saviour makes of this accident: for hence he takes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſhew his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, what miracles their faith ſhould worke, if it were true, and ſetled; that it ſhould not only have Trees, but the Earth, and Sea obedient to it, ſo that mountaines ſhould remoove, and the Sea ſtand ſtill at their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:180876:27"/>faith, were it not waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This is much: but the next priviledge is greater; namely, that they ſhould obtaine of GOD whatſoever they askt in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Name, obſerving but one condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, to forgive as they wold be forgive<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Me thinkes this is ſomething like mans ſtate in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, who had but one condition to obſerve to keepe himſelfe happy; even as Mankind heere, in the perſon of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, hath but one rule preſcribed, to reſtore it to GODS favour by forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:180876:27"/>that is, to forgive others, who repent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. Mankind, I ſay, not the Diſciples alone; for, in other places, our Saviour makes both the duty and condition generall. Therfore looke to thy faith whoſoever thou art, for thou art warn'd as well as the Diſciples: and, if thou looke thy prayer ſhould find enterance by it, to obtaine forgivenes in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> beleeve this one thing ere thou begin to pray, That <hi>Faith</hi> is not <hi>faith,</hi> unleſſe <hi>Love</hi> goe with it: thou muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:180876:28"/>therefore, and that from the bottome of thy Heart, thy repentant Brother, (which is a worke of <hi>Love</hi>) or elſe thou canſt never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given.</p>
            <p>With the end of this doctrine wee are come now with our Saviour into <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and no ſooner there, but entred into the Temple; which, to this purpoſe, lay next the gate that led to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanle,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> might have the readier entrance into his owne houſe. There he hath not beene long a teaching, (ſaith S.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:180876:28"/>
               <hi>Matthew</hi>) and that as hee was walking (ſaith <hi>S. Marke</hi>) becauſe hee would looſe no time, but the cheife Preiſts, and Scribes, and Elders of the people, all men of authority (and therefore the Phariſies, who were a kind of <hi>Monkes,</hi> were not with them) are upon him to know his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. It was a part of High Treaſon, if they would have conſidered it, for them to call him to account for his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, from whom they held theirs: for, if they were High Preiſts,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:180876:29"/>hee was their King; if they were Scribes, hee was their High Preiſt; if they were Elders, hee was from everlaſting. For this cauſe hee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not to anſwere them directly, but by another queſtion, touching the Baptiſme of <hi>Iohn, whether it was from Heaven, or of men?</hi> This was a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they were ſure to be taken in, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they anſwer'd: for, if the ſaid it was of men, they feared the people, leaſt they ſhould ſtone the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe all men held <hi>Iohn</hi> for a Prophet: if
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:180876:29"/>they ſaid from Heaven, they condemned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for not beleeving <hi>Iohn,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſt</hi> neither, whom <hi>Iohn</hi> had taught, and pointed at, when hee ſaid, <hi>Behold the Lambe of God:</hi> and againe, when hee ſaid, <hi>This is hee who commeth after mee, but is greater then I, whoſe ſhoe latchet I am not worthy to unlooſe.</hi> Therefore when they would not ſpeake truth, for ſhameing, and durſt not ſpeake falſhood, for endangering themſelves, they (unfitly for men of place, and learning)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180876:30"/>put the queſtion off, with <hi>Wee cannot tell:</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not confeſſe the truth that they knew, neither ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will our Saviour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready enform'd, yet, contrary to their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, deny to know that which they knew well enough. For they had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences enough, not only to teach, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force upon them alſo, that our Lords authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty could not but be from GOD; but Pride would not ſuffer them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him. For
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:180876:30"/>this cauſe, hee, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the proud, and gives grace to the humble, cared not to give grace to them who were not humble enough to ſtoop to his authority, but leaves them to the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of their harts, even till they come to that height of malice, as to crucifie him who ſought their Salvation. This teaches us to take heed how we oppoſe our ſelves to the knowne Truth, leaſt wee bee left to our ſelves, as theſe High Preiſts, Scribes, &amp; Elders were, to crucifie
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:180876:31"/>againe the Lord of life, and make a mocke of him.</p>
            <p>That they were left to themſelves, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> even to the hardnes of their harts, the event not only ſhewes, but our Saviour alſo, as a Prophet, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues them of, before it come into act. Firſt, in the Parable of a certaine Man, who had two Sonnes; the one ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne of tongue, yet ready of hand, after his penitence; the other ready of his promiſe, but as ſlow to performe itin his deede: for, the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:180876:31"/>one denyes to worke in his Fathers Vineyard, yet after repents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and goes; the other promiſes to goe, in faire and forward tearmes ſaying, <hi>I will Sir,</hi> but goes not. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in the Parable of the houſhoulder, who let his Vineyard out to ill husbandmen, who both denied him his Rent, beat his ſervants, and ſlew his Sonne, all whom he had ſent, one after another, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it. Thirdly, in the Parable of the wedding dinner of the Kings
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:180876:32"/>Sonne, to which they that were bidden, that is, the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who were firſt called,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>10.6.</hi>
               </note> both in the time of the Law,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>1.16.</hi>
               </note> and of the Goſpell, of any nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, refuſed to come. In which Parables how carefull is our Lord to ſet the Sinne they were to commit, before the eyes both of Preiſt and People, in his right co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours? therefore hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it once, twiſe, and thriſe over, that they may take the better notice of it. And them, by this meanes, hee left inexcuſable: ſo ſhall wee
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:180876:32"/>bee alſo, unleſſe wee take warning by their example. For our duty is, as well as theirs, firſt, to worke in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, when hee calls us; for, though wee bee his Sonnes, he will not allow us to bee idle: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to pay him his Rent, for our Farme, or Leaſe of life he truſts us with; for, though wee bee his Farmers, wee hold not of him in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, or for a Roſe in winter: Thirdly, when hee calls us to his Table, to come like men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on our wedding
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:180876:33"/>garment; for it is neither for his honour, nor our credit, that wee ſhould come in our old rags. In a word: wee muſt come to GOD, as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, in our courſe outſide, when hee would have us to worke, but like Holy-day-men, as if wee had not wrought at all, when our labour is done; that is, not making ſhew of, or truſting in any thing wee have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. For this is GODS manner of entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Thou muſt firſt come to him in thy rags, that is, ſuch build as thou
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:180876:33"/>haſt, and worke out thy freedome after that thou muſt put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> for thy Garment; by expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to thy power in thy outward actions, whom thou haſt layd up for thy righteouſnes in thy heart, and then thou art a gueſt for GODS Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Yea, thus thou muſt pay him thy Rent, by ſorrow for thy ſinne, and a broken heart, and then thou ſhalt be bidden, or called in to the wedding among thoſe whom GOD will receive to his Dinner: and thither alſo thou muſt carry thy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:180876:34"/>with thee, not ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for place, as if it were thine of due, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Humble thy ſelfe, and thou ſhalt bee exalted; exalt thy ſelfe before GOD and thou ſhalt bee brought low.</p>
            <p>Theſe admonitions, which, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> beeing thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, might, and ſhould have beene medicinall to <hi>Chriſts</hi> enemies, on the contrary fretted them to the gall: ſo that, to bee avenged, they ſet the <hi>Herodians</hi> firſt, to entrap him in a queſtion of State, that hee might bee brought within the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:180876:34"/>compaſſe of Treaſon: next, the Sadduces, with a queſtion of their Law, that hee might come within compaſſe of Hereſie: after that, a Lawyer to tempt him, if he could entrap him of Ignorance, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able his Teaching: but when he had put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all off with wiſdome, fit for Wiſdome to ſpeake, at length hee is ſo bold as to aske them a queſtion, (ſeeing they will needs, bee ſo bold with him) concerning his Divinity. The queſtion is taken out of the booke of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:180876:35"/>
               <hi>Pſalmes:</hi> In which, the holy Prophet <hi>David</hi> calls <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Lord, in the Spirit (of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) who was his Sonne according to the fleſh, ſo long before acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> that was his Sonne, in the fleſh of his Manhood, was his Lord, in the Spirit of his Godhead. This if our Saviours adverſaries would have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, they durſt not have gone about to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap him; and then the queſtion had beene eaſy alſo: For it was no more
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:180876:35"/>but this, How doth <hi>David</hi> in Spirit call <hi>Chriſt</hi> Lord, ſeeing hee was his Sonne? An eaſie queſtion, if they would either have beleeved <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> on his Prophecy, or <hi>Chriſt</hi> on his word, or the miracles which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed them both. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> his miracles were ſuch, as evinced both the prophecyes that had gone of him to bee true, and him to bee the <hi>Meſſias</hi> that was prophecyed of, for they were all done in his owne Name, which ſhewed him evidently
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:180876:36"/>to bee GOD; becauſe none can ſay of himſelfe I charge, or I command, but hee that is higheſt: therefore the Apoſtles ſaid ever, In the Name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> or ſome ſuch like words. For this cauſe, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> taught in this forme, <hi>I ſay unto you,</hi> all men marvailed: and when hee ſaid, <hi>Thy ſinns are forgiventhee,</hi> the Phariſies murmered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſaid (and faid truely) none could forgive ſinnes after that manner, but GOD alone. Theſe things
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:180876:36"/>might have taught theſe captious poſers, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was GOD, if they would have laid them to heart: and on the other ſide they might know as well, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>Davids</hi> Sonne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh, by his Mother, the Bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, who was both of <hi>Davids</hi> Tribe, and family. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> therefore might well call him Lord, as hee was GOD, who was his Sonne as hee was Man. But their pride having taken the right anſwer from them, they
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:180876:37"/>had not one word to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; which ſtrucke them with ſuch a confuſion that they turned their backs, like men van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht, neither ever durſt any after that Day aske him any queſtion.</p>
            <p>Now are their mouths ſtopt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> &amp; our Saviour hath leaſure to breath awhile: which hee doth not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, no more then hee did, before this time, ſtrike his enemies dumbe, (which hee could eaſily have done) to enjoy his quiet. Hee could have done it eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it appeares out of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:180876:37"/>the ſtory of his taking, in S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>18.6.</hi>
               </note> where hee ſtrikes his enemies back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the ground with a word; hee could therefore have long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe ſtopped their mouths, but hee would not: yea, hee could eaſily have put them all to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but his pleaſure was they ſhould goe on; partly, becauſe hee would have his wiſdome and theirs compared together to the full, that it might appeare which was the true one; partly, becauſe hee would have it ſeene,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:180876:38"/>what fury hee had to ſtrive with, what hatred to overcome. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſoone as theſe fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are gone with their nets, our Lord warnes the people at large, of ſuch falſe Teachers as they bee. Eſpecially, hee denounces wo upon wo, againſt the Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, who were a ſect much like the Ieſuites now a dayes, for auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſtrictnes of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and therefore did more hurt then any other: and Stateſmen they were too, like unto them, as may appeare
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:180876:38"/>out of their ſtory in <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus.</hi> That they were ſuch people as with great violence, and heat of corrupt Zeale follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their intents, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully prevailed by that meanes, our Saviour himſelfe expreſſes of them when hee ſayes, THEY compaſſe Sea, and Land to make one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyte, and when they have him they make him twofolde the child of Hell more then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Theſe falſe Teachers our Lord is more earneſt againſt, becauſe they miſled his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:180876:39"/>owne, one, only choſen people at that time, in regard of viſible, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane knowledg; for GOD had no Temple then, nor Church viſible in all the world, ſave in <hi>Iury.</hi> Which makes him ſo tender over it, that howſoever it was, or had beene bent againſt him, yet hee cannot but pitie it, &amp; greive at their deſtruction: therefore he ends the Chapter in which hee denounced ſo many woes againſt the wolves that deſtroyed his flocke, with a pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lamentation over
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:180876:39"/>
               <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> For heare him, thou that paſſes by, how deerly hee bewailes his owne Cities wofull madnes, that forſooke him to take part with Murderers; <hi>Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>thou that killeſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent to thee; how often would I have gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee as a hen gathereth her chickens under her winges, and yee would not?</hi> Much like unto <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> affection to, and mourning over his dead Sonne <hi>Abſalon; Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Abſalon,</hi> (ſaith hee)
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:180876:40"/>
               <hi>my Sonne Abſalon, would God I had died for thee.</hi> Thus holy <hi>David,</hi> as a father, laments his deere Sonne, and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as a Saviour, his deere Citie. But our Saviour exceedes: for his ſorrow was both more deepe, (though it have not ſo many words of repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to expreſſe it) and more ſeaſonable alſo; for <hi>Abſalon</hi> was paſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery when <hi>David</hi> mourn'd; but <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had time to repent, when our Lord wept over it. It had time, I ſay, but it would not: nay <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:180876:40"/>ſayes ſo, but they knew not the time of their viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; therfore hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyes of it, <hi>Behold your houſe ſhal be left unto you deſolate:</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy was fulfilled in the Emperour <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> dayes, and continues ſo unto our time. The leſſon wee have heere to take out is, for Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that they bee not like to theſe Prieſts and Phariſies; for Hearers, that they bee not like <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> leaſt both Prieſt and People doe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh together.</p>
            <p>By this time now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:180876:41"/>night to draw on, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> therefore leaves the Temple for this day;<note place="margin">For the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury was at the going out of the Temple, <hi>2. Chro. 24. S.</hi>
               </note> which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, firſt, by the <hi>Story</hi> of the poore widdow, whom hee commends for caſting her whole ſubſtance (which a poore widdow might ſoone doe) into the Treaſury. Secondly,<note place="margin">Which muſt bee, on the outſide.</note> by his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſhewing him the buildings and ſtones of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy upon that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That there was not a ſtone, upon a ſtone, which ſhould not bee throwne downe:</hi> which two <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:180876:41"/>teach us two excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent leſſons: Firſt, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> accepts of the Heart more then the Hand, and of the givers affection, then the riches of the gifts (for the poore widdow gave but two mites:) Secondly, that there is no worke ſo glorious, (no not buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Temples) which can ſtand before GOD, when it failes either in ſubſtance, or affection; for even GODS owne Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could not pleaſe him, neither might it ſtand, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Ceremonial Law, under which it was
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:180876:42"/>erected, was once abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated.</p>
            <p>Form the Temple aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is come to the mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> there hee ſitts downe, and at his Diſciples requeſt, enlarges the Prophecy hee had delivered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the deſtruction of the Temple, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; which, with much efficacy of doctrine and exhortation, he finiſhes in a whole Chapter. And the more inſtant hee is in it, becauſe it concernes not <hi>Iury</hi> only, but the whole world in generall (whoſe fate depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:180876:42"/>the fate of the Church whatſoever it otherwiſe imagine) whoſe deſtruction (therefore) is figured in the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And that hee may prepare all men for his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, the time when theſe things ſhal happen, he joynes for this cauſe, to the prophecy, a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the ten Virgins, whereof five were wiſe, five were fooliſh. The wiſe brought oyle for their Lampes; but the fooliſh neglecting this part of providence, after they have aſſayed, in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:180876:43"/>vaine, to borrow, in their abſence the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome comming, enters into his houſe, makes the doores bee ſhut, and ſo they are excluded from the Marriage of their Soules unto GOD. This Parable that it may bee better underſtood, there followes it a moſt plaine and expreſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the laſt Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the rigor of it, which ſhall bee when the world ſhall have an end: in which Iudgment, the godly ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into everlaſting Ioy, and the wicked caſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:180876:43"/>into utter darknes, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite eternall paine, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Devill, and his Angells. There is another Parable by Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> mixt with theſe; and that is, of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Talents, which the Lord gave forth to his ſervants, at his going to his Travaile: but this in order of time, belongs to the weeke before, when our Lord firſt had a ſight of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> as may appeare, <hi>Luke.</hi> 19.12.</p>
            <p>Now is Night already come, and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> it may be, lookt for in <hi>Bethany;</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:180876:44"/>but from this time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hee never returnes thither, nor comes in any bed, till hee bee layd in the Rocke by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> to ſleepe his three dayes ſleepe; from which cold, and hard bed, hee roſe but once, to lie downe no more. This Saint <hi>Luke</hi> hath obſerved,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.37.</note> who tells us expreſly, that in the day time <hi>Chriſt</hi> taught in the Temple, but at Night he went out and abode in the Mount that is called <hi>Olives:</hi> which words ſeeing they cannot bee underſtoode of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:180876:44"/>Nights that are paſt (in which hee lay in <hi>Betha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>) it remaines that they belong to this Night, and thoſe that follow, to the time of his Paſſion. It was but a cold lodging that Mount <hi>Olives</hi> could afford our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: A field-bed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other Canopy but the vault of Heaven, (GODS high Starre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber;) or any, either Pillow, or Rugge, but the greene Earth: yet thus hee choſe to bee an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample unto us in watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it may bee hee was at the ſame time in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:180876:45"/>praying alſo; both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>Watch and Pray,</hi> which joynes prayer with watching; as alſo of his Practiſe, at other times, in which theſe two are not ſevered. The ſame duties that hee might ſtirre up his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples unto alſo, hee foretells them of his <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maath</hi> 26.2.</note> after hee hath finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſayings before mentioned, to let them ſee what neede they had to watch, and pray with him alſo. It is not likely, but that this deſire of our Saviours tooke effect in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:180876:45"/>his Diſciples. Let us ſuppoſe that it did ſo; and then wee have a band of ſpirituall Souldiers watching heere, or elſe a company of Saintes praying, ſuch as all the Earth (I had almoſt ſaid Heaven) cannot ſhew the like. If ever wee will pray then, let us doe it now; for we cannot have better company: and if wee watch too, ſo it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy not Nature, wee ſhall bee like <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in whom onely wee hope to prevaile. And thus let us take our leave of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or rather attend
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:180876:46"/>on him, for this Night time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <head>Meditations for WEDNESDAY.</head>
            <p>NOw begins the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophe</hi> of this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy to come in; for this Morning all <hi>Chriſts</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies meete together, and take bloody counſell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him. And to helpe them on, <hi>Iudas Iſcariot,</hi> (whoſe bloody mind was never pleaſed with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſince hee blamed
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:180876:46"/>his coveteouſnes, for grudging at <hi>Maries</hi> powring her pretious oyntment on his head,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.3.</note> the <hi>Saturday</hi> laſt paſt,) hee like a covetous wretch, to make up his loſſe, comes in with his, <hi>What will yee give mee, and I will betray Chriſt unto you?</hi> The word was no ſooner ſpoken, but the bargaine was driven, money pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, hands ſtricken, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſold. But for what thinke yee? Even for thirtie pieces of ſilver. A goodly price to value him at, whoſe blood, even
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:180876:47"/>the leaſt drop of it, was of worth to purchaſe Heaven and Earth. Thus ungodly men, like prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls, make away their wealth, for nothing: but let us by their example, bee brought to bee more wary, and thrifty of our ſpirituall riches, leaſt wee fall into extreame miſery: and that the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe GOD is auſtere, and will one day have an account of all our ſpendings.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whiles his Death is a plotting, it is very likely that our Saviour is a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:180876:47"/>teaching: yet what hee taught this Day, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts bee all ſilent in; belike the Holy Ghoſt meant to leave us time enough, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning yeſterdaies long leſſon. And yet this Day, for a neede, will afford a man matter enough for meditation. For hee that can but endure to take a view of the cruell ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of <hi>Chriſts</hi> enemies, may find what will give him ſufficient occaſion to bewaile his owne ſinnes, and wonder at theirs, who were actors in ſo bloody a deſigne.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:180876:48"/>Or if theſe ſeeme too diſmall to ſettle our thoughts on, let us but caſt our eyes upon our Saviours patience, who was not mooved with all that was deviſed againſt him, no not ſo much as to breake off his ordinary excerciſe of preaching, by that meanes, even then ſeeking to win them, that ſought to deſtroy him; it will a little ſweeten the bitter of that which went before.</p>
            <p>And if wee ſtay a little, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to looke upon the faire face of this vertue in our Saviour, it will bee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:180876:48"/>worth the copying out. <hi>Tertullian</hi> hee deſcribes Patience on this manner. <hi>Vultus illi tranquillus &amp; placidus, frons pura, nullâ moeroris aut iraerugoſitate contracta, remiſſa aequèlae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in modum ſupercilia, &amp;c.</hi> i. Her looke is quiet, and gentle, her forehead plaine and ſmooth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever a wrinkle of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or ſorrow; her eylids let downe equally with Ioy, and her eyes caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground, of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility nevertheleſſe, but not of greife; her colour confident, ſuch as they have who are guiltleſſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:180876:49"/>and ſecure; her mouth ſealed up with ſilence; often ſhaking her head at the Devill, and ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him with a threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning laughter; her attire white, neither ſtrait to her Body, nor looſe and fluent, but plaine and ſeemly; her place is above the Clouds, where neither ſtorme, nor tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt can ſhake her; the Holy Spirit himſelfe lends her his Throne, to reſt her in, where ſhee ſits as a Queene, bee the Earth never ſo unquiet againſt her. Thus hee deſcribes this vertue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:180876:49"/>as if ſhee had put off her vaile, that hee might take a true pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traict of her face.</p>
            <p>Yet a better deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Patience may bee had, nevertheleſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> out of our Saviours owne perſon; and ſo wee ſhall make Patience, not a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, but a manly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as it is indeed, and appeares to bee ſo, in that it makes women to bee men, at leaſt more then women: neither can any womaniſh effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate heart ever bee truly patient, but will alwaies bee grudging and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:180876:50"/>Well then: let our Saviour bee unto us the true picture of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,<note place="margin">The Comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his perſon, I take to bee evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of the place of Saint <hi>Luke, Luke. 2.52. And Ieſus increaſed in wiſdome, and ſtature, and favour, with God, and men.</hi> This is by ſome aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the cauſe, why the women wept ſo faſt for him whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee went t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>his executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and let us take the deſcription of it from him. His counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was faire, and full of Majeſty, as ſome thinke, and as <hi>Lentulus</hi> his letter deſcribes him, even as the face of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is Heavenly, and reverent: according unto others, (and ſo the Scripture ſeemes to make him) not outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lovely or beautiful, no more is Patience a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vertue to looke on, but winns by inward
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:180876:50"/>worth, rather then by outward beauty: never was hee ſeene to laugh, (for Patience hath little time to bee merry in this world) but often to weepe; yet not much neither, but ſo as might ſhewe his affection, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then give way to it: his haire long, as <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> was, and his whole perſon farre ſtronger made then hee, to beare: his feete all bare ſave his ſandalls; a fit foundation for Patience to build on: his garment woven whole, from the top to the bottome, not one
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:180876:51"/>ſeame to divide it; much leſſe is it rent upon him, by impatience: his ſpeach full of grace, yet not much, but alway ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; in all his ſufferings not once heard to revile, or complaine, no not on the Croſſe; and which is more, not once to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a grone there: but, on the contrary, hee prayed even then for his perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, ſaying, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they doe:</hi> whileſt hee knowes, as upon this Day, the High Prieſts, and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices to bee plotting his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:180876:51"/>Death, yea buying and ſelling him, hee is labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſave them; who within two dayes after, he knew, would prefer a murderer before him, even then when it ſtood upon his life: when <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> returnes from his bloody bargaine, even from ſelling his Maſters head, hee never once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viles, or rates him, or caſts him off, yea when he goes actually to betray him, and outright, hee ſaies no more to him but this, <hi>That thou doeſt doe it quickly.</hi> If this bee not the perfect picture of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:180876:52"/>Patience, I know not where wee ſhall have it.</p>
            <p>Now theſe actions are our inſtructions, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſufferings are but a patterne for us, to take out the perfect worke of patience by. So ſaith Saint <hi>Peter: Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example to followe his ſteps; who did no ſinne, neither was there any guile found in his mouth; who when hee was reviled, reviled not againe, when hee ſuffered, hee threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not, but committed his cauſe to him that judgeth righteouſly.</hi> We
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:180876:52"/>have all need of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that after we have done the will of GOD, we may inherite the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for yet a little while and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry. Let us heare ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the word of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as it is laid down for us in Saint <hi>Iames: Be patient, my Brethren, untill the comming of the Lord: behold the huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man waiteth for the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, untill he receive the former and latter raine: be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent therfore and ſtabliſh
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:180876:53"/>your hearts, for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.</hi> The ſame Apoſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to patience, the meanes to make us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.2. <hi>My Brethren, count it ioy, when yee fall into many temptations, knowing that the triall of your faith worketh patience: and let patience have her perfect worke, that ye may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and entire, wanting nothing.</hi> This vertue whoſoever would have, hee is now at the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: for from <hi>Chriſt</hi> we muſt have it, or not at all. Let us then ſeeke for
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:180876:53"/>it in him, or to him for it, and ſo we may come to find it: and the rather let us doe it, becauſe our ſoules are not our owne (in this troubleſome world) without pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; <hi>for in patience</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi>) <hi>yee muſt poſſeſſe your Soules.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <head>Meditations for THURSDAY.</head>
            <p>A Little lightning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death, as on this day, hath our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, and but a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:180876:54"/>little neither, even while he is preparing and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Paſſeover: all the reſt of the day he is teaching, as may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably conjectured. But ere hee beginne to do that, he gives direction firſt, where he will have the Paſſeover made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for him, by ſending two of his Diſciples to a certaine man that ſhould meet them with a pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of water; by which, and other ſignes that hee gives, they ſhould know him to be the partie, whoſe houſe hee had choſen for the purpoſe.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:180876:54"/>This man, whom our Saviour ſent thus to, is obſerved (further) to have beene a Diſciple; for when the two who were ſent from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> meete with him, they ſay, <hi>The Maſter ſaith:</hi> which is noted to have beene the name that the followers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> called him by among themſelves; as it may appeare to be by <hi>Martha's</hi> words to <hi>Mary</hi> her ſiſter, <hi>The Maſter is come, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for thee.</hi> This being granted, that this man was a beleever, it will
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:180876:55"/>reſt uncertaine, whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> had beſpoken a roome of him before this, or no, for, if he was a Diſciple, he might ere this time have made it knowne to him, by word, as well as by reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that he would eate the Paſſeover in his houſe: and it helpes the conjecture a little, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his roome was ſo ready. But howſoever that might be done or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, or otherwiſe, certaine it is, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> foretelling, <hi>they ſhould meete him, bearing a pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of water,</hi> was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:180876:55"/>to confirme the Diſciples faith, &amp; ours. Alſo, in that his roome was ready dreſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Chriſt,</hi> beſides that it commends decency unto us, both in the man, and in it ſelfe, it ſerves alſo, to ſhew us how wee ſhould have our hearts prepared for our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; namely, that wee muſt cleanſe them, dreſſe them, trimme them, and alwayes have them fit to receive him: if wee give him the upper roome in them alſo, wee do but follow our example. Only let us take heede
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:180876:56"/>when he ſends his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that is, his Miniſters, that they find us not without our pitcher of water, that is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out teares of true peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in our eyes, that wee are no better prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to entertaine him.</p>
            <p>The next thing the holy Evangeliſts lead us to, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is the putting that in effect, which here was made way for. But before wee come to that, if it ſeeme ſtrange to any, which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> hath noted unto us, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Paſſeover was two dayes before the <hi>Iewes;</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:180876:56"/>(for theirs was on Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.14.</note> his on Thurſday) it may be the leſſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veilous to him, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders, how farre <hi>Chriſt</hi> was before them in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. And that might well ſerve for an anſwer, were it not that the law of GOD is ſo <hi>ſtrict</hi> in appointing the day on which the Paſſeover ſhould be kept.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.18.</note> But the undoing of this knot, is to be learned out of a cuſtome which the <hi>Iewes</hi> had taken up, ever ſince they came from <hi>Babiloa,</hi> and to gaine credit to it, aſcribed it to revelation
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:180876:57"/>from GOD, which was this. That if the Paſſeover fell neere the Sabbath day, it ſhould be defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red untill the Sabbath, that the people might not have two holy-daies ſo neere together, and ſo the commandement (belike) be endangered; <hi>Sixe dayes ſhaltthou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi> This was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the <hi>Iewes</hi> defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Paſſeover un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Saturday, which our Saviour kept upon Thurſday. For Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day was the legall day. Therefore <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who beſt knew the meaning of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:180876:57"/>his owne commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which they by ſcrupulouſnes miſ-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) kept that day, neither would give the leaſt example to make the law of GOD of none effect, by mans traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This keeping of the Paſſeover, was the laſt Ceremonial act, that ever our Saviour perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>Now, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſeeing wee have none of this dayes worke ſet downe by <hi>Chriſts</hi> pen-men, let us come unto that the evening affords us, which is full of many ſtrange occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:180876:58"/>The firſt thing in it, is the abrogating of the Sacramentall Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Paſſeover, and inſtituting that of the New, which wee call, by Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, the <hi>Supper of the Lord.</hi> And there are not many circumſtances to obſerve in the firſt of theſe: As firſt;</p>
            <p>That <hi>Chriſt</hi> abrogated the Legall Ceremonies, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> by fulfilling them, and inducing of better; for he kept both the right day, though the whole nation did otherwiſe,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:180876:58"/>and the right time of the day, the evening, and the right company, his Diſciples, and of thoſe, no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the twelve, who were his houſhould ſervants, and ever with him: as for his ſitting, whereas ſome thinke it is legall he ſhould have ſtood, it appeares out of <hi>Exodus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi>11.10.</note> that it was a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance not perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but proper to the time when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were to leave <hi>Aegypt:</hi> and that he obſerved the feaſt in an other mans houſe, the reaſon is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe hee had not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:180876:59"/>(more ſhame for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) one of his owne, no not a place to hide his head in.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> wee may obſerve about it, <hi>Chriſts</hi> deſire hee had to eate this Supper with his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: which himſelfe expreſſes moſt expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when hee ſayes, <hi>deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derio deſideravi, &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>I have vehemently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to eate this Paſſeover with you, before I ſuffer.</hi> As for a third circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which ſome ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that hee tooke the cup in the time of the Paſſeover, and gave it
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:180876:59"/>his diſciples to go among them, after the ſame manner that hee did, when hee inſtituted his owne Supper; it is by the learned obſerved to be ſpoken by Anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the action to belong to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment following, in which it is of the eſſence of it: therefore by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Evangeliſts it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned in that place. To let paſſe that then; theſe two, that wee are certaine of, have their uſe to us-ward: the firſt, to ſhew <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſtrictnes in doing the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:180876:60"/>will of his father, and fulfilling the Law for us, that wee might bee free from the burthen of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies: the ſecond, both to ſhew his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to mankind in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, in that he deſired ſo much to come once to the eating of his laſt Supper, that hee might make an end by it, of the bondage of Rites, and bring in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall freedome; as alſo his love to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in ſpeciall, for whoſe cauſe hee deſired the Paſſeover ſo earneſtly, that hee might have them at his owne table
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:180876:60"/>before hee left them, and let them ſee how lovingly hee parted from them: for this cauſe it is noted, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour had other meate beſides the Paſchall Lambe, that hee might receive his Diſciples the more liberally; for hee had a diſh of meate with a ſweete ſawce to it, which he dipped a ſopp in, and gave it to <hi>Iudas:</hi> and that this could not be the Paſchall Lambe it is evident, becauſe that had a ſawce indeede, but it was made of bitter herbes, not fit to dip
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:180876:61"/>bread in, ſignifying the bitter affliction, which their forefathers were delivered from in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſently after the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Paſſeover, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the waſhing of the Diſciples feete: which though it might be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to cuſtome in thoſe hot countries, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham waſhed the Angells feete: and the widowes,</hi> in <hi>Timothy, muſt be ſuch as had waſhed the Saints feete</hi> yet it may have alſo a Spiritual ſignification; namely, to ſhew how cleane they are to bee,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:180876:61"/>that come to the Supper of the Lord: alſo, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt waſh us him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or elſe all our waſhing is nothing worth: becauſe of which ſignification, this waſhing was put off, till after the Paſſeover, and before the Lords Supper; otherwiſe, by the cuſtome, and faſhion of the countrie, it ſhould have beene before them both, as may appeare out of <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.4.</note> After the waſhing ended, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſits downe againe, and having expounded what hee meant by his laſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:180876:62"/>action, namely, to teach his Diſciples humility and mutuall love; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo given a touch at the Traitor <hi>Iudas,</hi> whoſe feete among the reſt hee had waſhed, but his heart hee could not; he proceedes to inſtitute the Sacrament of his Supper. The intent of this Sacrament hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in part expreſſes; namely, that by break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bread, there ſhould bee a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the breaking of his body, and by powring of wine, the ſhedding of his blood,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:180876:62"/>continued untill his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. A remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance only, I ſay, for ſo ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Do this in remembrance of mee.</hi> Therefore they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the nature of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, that will have it, not a memoriall, but a corporall exhibition of the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the literall ſence of the words, <hi>This is my body.</hi> To anſwer whome, wee may heere note, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Bread, which he calls his body, and this Cup, which hee termes his blood, with his owne
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:180876:63"/>hands, before ever hee had a Spirituall Body; ſo that his Diſciples could not receive his body af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch manner as the Papiſts would have it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, becauſe it was yet a naturall one, and not after that manner communicable: unleſſe wee will ſay, that the Apoſtles received the Sacrament after another manner then wee do; and they indeede, could not receive <hi>Chriſts</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Body, which yet was not, but wee do.</p>
            <p>After this Sacrament ended, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> while the Table
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:180876:63"/>is not yet taken away, nor any one riſen, our Saviour beginnes to bee troubled, and to expreſſe more plainly the treaſon that <hi>Iudas</hi> had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt him. Yet this complaint, it is a wonder to ſee how ſweetly hee carries: for, though hee knew the Traitor, and had moſt juſt reaſon to have diſcloſed him with utmoſt deteſtation, yet hee never detects him to any, but his beloved diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple <hi>Iohn,</hi> and that upon inquiry. For whereas it is read how <hi>Iudas</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:180876:64"/>asked, with the reſt of the Diſciples (like an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent wretch) <hi>is it I Maſter?</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, <hi>Thou haſt ſaid it,</hi> it is noted, that hee ſpake theſe words ſo ſoftly and ſecretly in his eare, that the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor only heard them. And when as Saint <hi>Iohn, Chriſts</hi> beloved Diſciple, at <hi>Peters</hi> requeſt, asked him who hee meant, it is obſerved alſo, that hee received the ſigne in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, <hi>Hee it is, to whome I ſhall give a ſop:</hi> for, if theſe things had beene done openly, the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:180876:64"/>could not afterward have beene ignorant of <hi>Chriſts</hi> words which hee ſpake to <hi>Iudas, That thou doeſt, doe it quickly:</hi> which nevertheleſſe it is manifeſt they were; for they thought <hi>Chriſt</hi> had ſent him to buy ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And therefore, whereas it is ſuppoſed alſo by ſome, that the Traitor was then ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, when it is ſaid, <hi>Hee that dippeth his hand with me in the diſh, ſhall betray mee,</hi> it cannot be true; for (beſides the former reaſon) it is but the ſame phraſe which <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:180876:65"/>uſed in the like caſe: <hi>Hee that ate bread with mee hath lift up his heele againſt mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And certainly this was a miraculous, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> or (to ſpeake more properly) a divine moderation in our Saviour, that hee never once detected his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall enemie, or broke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to paſſion againſt him, though he knew him: but, on the contrary, hee reached him a ſopp, to winne him from his bloody and violent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if ſo hee would, or could have beene chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for that action of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:180876:65"/>reaching the ſoppe, was an action of love, as Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is among us, and ſo underſtood by all the Diſciples, except Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> to whome it was a private ſigne: ſo that if <hi>Iudas</hi> could have taken it ſo, he had then beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called; and in that he did not, he was left more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable.</p>
            <p>That hee tooke it not ſo, the ſequell ſhewes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> and the effect which his inward thoughts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently breake into; for our Saviours ſoppe wrought upon <hi>Iudas,</hi> as good Phyſick doth upon
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:180876:66"/>corrupt bodies, which makes them worſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, &amp; the diſeaſe more deadly. So was it with this Murderer; for no ſooner hath he taken the ſop, but hee goes forth, to accompliſh his curſed malice. But curſed bee his malice, for it was cruell, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſecret let not our Soules enter. Better it is to admire <hi>Chriſts</hi> divine moderation, and imitate it, then excuſe <hi>Iudas</hi> his fact, or leſſen the greateſt ſinne, that the nature of man is capable of: better it is to ſtay with <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:180876:66"/>in the chamber, then fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low <hi>Iudas</hi> to the High Prieſts: better, in a word, to ſuffer with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then betray him with <hi>Iudas;</hi> and if any man beleeve not this, let him but looke to the end that <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> makes the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and no longer to it.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould make uſe of every thing that was done after this, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this day, would not be this dayes only meditation, but muſt needes extend to the next: which hath mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nevertheleſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:180876:67"/>in it ſelfe, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it ſelfe, but alſo for a mans whole life. I will therefore runne over things, with what brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I am able.</p>
            <p>The next thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.24.</note> is the Diſciples ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for ſuperiority; an untimely ambition: after that,<note place="margin">ver. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſts</hi> exhortaton to humility, and unity; a friendly admonition: the next, is the foretelling of <hi>Peters</hi> fall;<note place="margin">ver. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> a propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prevention: after that, an arming of his Diſciples in generall,<note place="margin">ver. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt perſecution; a loving premunition:
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:180876:67"/>which is followed with a promiſe of reſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>14.1.</hi> and <hi>16.</hi> ver. ſo to the end of the Chap.</note> and a comforter on earth, even GOD the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt himſelfe; an endleſſe conſolation.</p>
            <p>After theſe ſpeeches, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> riſeth from Table, to goe unto the place where hee was to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed: yet entring into a new diſcourſe, he tarries within doores, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſo long, till he hath made an end of that excellent Sermon, (his Swans ſong) which is left us in the fifteenth, and ſixteenth Chapter of Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> which Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:180876:68"/>hee ends with a <hi>prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> his <hi>prayer</hi> with ſinging an <hi>hymne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30.</note> (whence, perhaps, our cuſtome of ending Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons after that manner ariſes,) and ſo goes out to the Mount of <hi>Olives.</hi> Some are of opinion, that the Sermon before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, was preached by the way, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> went to <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of the wiſe man, <hi>Wiſdome cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the ſtreetes:</hi> but it is againe anſwered, that the way is not long enough for it, unleſſe hee ſhould make ſtops in it, which
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:180876:68"/>is unprobable: neither is it likely, that on the night (for ſo it was now) <hi>Chriſt</hi> would ſtand and teach in the ſtreetes, and ſing alſo an <hi>hymne;</hi> which Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> tells us hee did upon his going out into the Mount of <hi>Olives.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Through this Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> was the way into the Garden of <hi>Gethſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane;</hi> and that Garden is the end of our Lords journey for this time. Into which aſſoone as hee is entered, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes the bitter cup of the Paſſion to be reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:180876:69"/>unto him, figured by the bitter herbes in the Paſſeover. The very ſight of this Cup, ere ever it came to his lips, was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bring a deadly heavines, even upon his Soule. It was now high time, then, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> to pray; which hee doeth once, againe, and againe, in theſe words, <hi>Father, if it be poſſible, le this Cup paſſe from mee.</hi> Yet are we not to thinke, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> would have this Cup paſſe from him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede; for he ſaith him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Shall I not drinke of the Cup that my Father
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:180876:69"/>hath given mee?</hi> But hee prayed thus, to let us ſee what reſolution Gods juſtice is of; it will not be mooved, when GOD hath once abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to puniſh ſinne, not though <hi>Chriſt</hi> pray for it; nay though hee himſelfe, in our perſon, be the patient.</p>
            <p>The whiles <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a praying, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> his Diſciples are a ſleeping; and that ſo heavily, that his twiſe comming to them, upon his firſt, and ſecond praying, could not keepe them waking, no not though hee chide them
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:180876:70"/>ſharply for their drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. It was a pitifull weight of ſinne, that made our Saviour Soule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heavy unto Death, and the Diſciples Bodies, to a deadly and unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſleepe. But this was not all: for it wrung a bloody ſweate (O the deadly weight of ſinne!) out of our Saviour, ſuch as never man ſweat the like in all points; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, layd him upon the ground groveling, in a moſt grievous ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſuch a one, as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell came downe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, from heaven;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:180876:70"/>for earthly comforters failed, and all they could have done, had beene little worth.</p>
            <p>Scarce is this agony over, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> and the bloody Sweate wiped from our Saviours face, but <hi>Iudas</hi> comes to apprehend him: which though hee could not have done without <hi>Chriſts</hi> permiſſion, for all the High Prieſts au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, (which was made manifeſt, when our Lord ſtruck downe them that came to take him, with a word of his mouth,) yet hee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.6.</note> nevertheleſſe, his
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:180876:71"/>curſed intent: ſo that though <hi>Peter</hi> reſiſt, and ſmite of <hi>Malchus</hi> his eare, yet <hi>Iudas</hi> prevailes, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is taken: neither can they be intreated to let him goe, though hee plead his innocency, and heale his enemie with a touch, (even <hi>Malchus</hi>) to let them ſee how farre hee was from hating them, notwithſtanding all their injury. But their hearts were hardned; therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt needes ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Next unto this, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes <hi>Chriſts</hi> examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before the High
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:180876:71"/>Prieſts, full of injuſtice and ſubornation. In the time of which ungodly proceedings, falls out a pitifull accident, which is, <hi>Peters</hi> deniall of his Maſter: which though it might ſeeme to admit of ſome excuſe, in that the temptation was ſtrong, even ſuch as, not long ſince, had made all <hi>Chriſts</hi> followers forſake him and flee; yet being thriſe—over committed, and that, after having beene forwarned of it, wee muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that it was a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous crime, eſpecially,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:180876:72"/>in that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was now (even as S. <hi>Peters</hi> faith was) upon his triall. Yet this wound, though it was the harder cure, <hi>Chriſt</hi> heales more eaſily then hee did that which <hi>Malchus</hi> received; for, that was healed by a touch, this only by loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king backe: for aſſoone as <hi>Chriſt</hi> look't backe, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> came to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, went out, and wept bitterly.</p>
            <p>As the Devill in his limbes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> is thus buſy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> ſo is hee himſelfe, the while, againſt <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for hee
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:180876:72"/>ſtirres up his good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the High Prieſts, and their company, to vexe him, not only, as before, by trapping in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories, but alſo by reviling him, ſpitting upon him, buffetting him, and mocking him. And now their malice is riſen to an height, it is time to make an end for this day, or rather this night, and ſo they doe: or rather the time it ſelfe doth for them, becauſe their malice had no end. For having ſit up all night about a worke of darknes, they are not
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:180876:73"/>aſhamed to proſecute it the next day; to which we are (GOD aſſiſting) the next to proceed: but let us take heede wee do it with another affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then they did; for if Saint <hi>Peter</hi> fell, that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed indeed, but a farre off, what will become of them that draw neere to perſecute?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thine Agony, and bloody Sweate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good Lord deliver us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:180876:73"/>
            <head>Meditations for FRIDAY.</head>
            <p>NOw beginnes the diſmalleſt Morning to appeare, that ever ſaw the Sunne: it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile if ſhe bluſh when ſhee riſes, to ſee ſuch bloody practiſes goe on, as the High Prieſts, and their ungodly Fraternity make her conſcious of. Yet one joyfull Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle ſhee hath, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, to cheare her ſelfe with, and that is the death of <hi>Iudas</hi> the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; who repenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:180876:74"/>(for he had beene of <hi>hriſts</hi> company, and therfore had ſome touch, though not of grace, in him) comes and reſtores the money he had taken for his Lord and Maſter, to the High Prieſts (if hee had ſtayed heere, there had beene ſome hope: but) after falling into deſpaire, hee is not at quiet, till hee hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged <hi>Chriſts</hi> quarrell on himſelfe, with his owne hands, which had taken the Money; for he went a way, and hanged himſelfe. Yet doeth not Gods juſtice ſtay here
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:180876:74"/>neither; for, as hee was hanging, his body broke in ſunder, and all his bowells guſhed out, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had no bowells of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion towards his Maſter. As for his Soule, aſſoone as ever it left his execrable body, it begun preſently to inherit thoſe curſes which the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> had layd up for him of old,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 109.6.</note> 
               <hi>Set thou a wicked man over him, and let Satan ſtand at his right hand: when he ſhalbe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed let him be condemned, and let his prayer become ſinne: let his dayes be few, and let another take his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:180876:75"/>office, &amp;c.</hi> Thus is GOD juſt upon his enemies, that we may learne to feare him.</p>
            <p>It will not be amiſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by the way here, to tell how the money was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed which <hi>Iudas</hi> brought backe to the High Prieſts, for the ſtrange qualitie of the field that was bought with it: for it is reported, that the nature of that ground is ſuch, as if a ſtrangers body be layd in it, (for it was bought to bury ſtrangers in) it conſumes it to the bone in foure and twenty houres, which it doeth
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:180876:75"/>not to any other Body, ſave thoſe it was appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to when it was bought. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this,<note place="margin">Adrichom.</note> mine author tells, that <hi>Helena,</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Queene-Mother of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> cauſing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine loades of this earth to bee brought to <hi>Rome,</hi> into the field that is now called the <hi>Holy field,</hi> it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the vertue there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and conſumes only ſtrangers bodies, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Romanes.</hi> which if it be true, it ſeemes, GOD would have the earth thus mark't to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the memory of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:180876:76"/>bloody money by which it was purchaſed; and therefore he gave it a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to conſume ſtrangers bodies ere they could corrupt, refuſing the <hi>Iewes,</hi> to ſhew how they had loſt their priviledge to their owne land, by crucifying their Lord, and ſtrangers began to be poſſeſt of it: alſo to teach us that his hope is neareſt incorruption, who is the greateſt ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from the ſinne of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that is, crucifying <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us returne to our Saviour againe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> who all
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:180876:76"/>this while ſtood looſe, though hee had beene brought bound to the High Prieſts; belike they had looſed him to try if they could make him bely himſelfe by faire meanes: which when they cannot prevaile in, firſt they bind him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and then carrie him ſo bound to <hi>Pilate,</hi> not privately, or with a few, but the whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of them together, to make the action more notable. When hee is come to <hi>Pilate,</hi> firſt they accuſe him of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt <hi>Ceſar;</hi>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:180876:77"/>though it was enough knowne, that hee had publiquely in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple taught of late, that <hi>Ceſar</hi> ſhould not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the things that were <hi>Ceſars.</hi> next, they lay ſedition to his charge, as if hee ſtirred the people to rebellion; though they knew as well, that hee refuſed the peoples offer when they would have made him King: yet thus ſhameleſſe are <hi>Chriſts</hi> accuſers, to appeale him of matters that were evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently untrue: and this <hi>Pilate</hi> may be found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:180876:77"/>to have taken notice of, therefore hee tried more wayes then one to deliver <hi>Chriſt:</hi> for, firſt hee would have put him off to the High Prieſts and Rulers, who hee knew could not put him to death becauſe that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority was taken away from them: after, beeing driven to examine him himſelfe, hee proteſts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in <hi>Chriſts</hi> behalfe, that hee could find no fault in him: upon that, <hi>Chriſt</hi> his accuſers begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to bee more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alledging that he had wronged both
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:180876:78"/>
               <hi>Ceſar</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> in ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as ſoone as ever <hi>Pilate</hi> heares <hi>Herod</hi> named hee ſeekes to put off the matter to him, and therfore ſends <hi>Chriſt</hi> unto him, as belonging to his Iuriſdiction: when <hi>Herod</hi> could find nothing worthy of death in him neither, but ſends him backe to <hi>Pilate</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touchtin his body (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>a garment of ſcorne</hi> that hee had put upon him) <hi>Pilate</hi> tries a pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy to free our Saviour,<note place="margin">A white garment. Adrichom<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Th. Terrae Sanctae.</note> by comparing him with the moſt grievous male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:180876:78"/>that had long been in Iayle, one <hi>Barrabas;</hi> which he did on hope to deliver him by vertue of a cuſtome the <hi>Iewes</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> which was, to have one ſet free to them, whom of two they ſhould chooſe. But when againſt his hope, and all probability, they refuſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and chuſe <hi>Barrabas,</hi> yet here hee leaves not to ſtrive for him; but firſt he calls for water, and waſhes his hands, proteſting by that Ceremony, that he would not have any of <hi>Chriſts</hi> blood cleave to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:180876:79"/>his hands, but it ſhould all be upon them, if they ſhed it: when that would not ſerve, he tries yet an other pollicy, unlawfull indeede, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the moſt effectuall in humane worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome he could deviſe, as the caſe then ſtood; namely, to give our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Lord to be moſt cruelly whipped, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thorne, and clothed with purple, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a reede in his hand, for a Scepter, to bee mocked of his Soldiers, ſpitt on, ſmitten on the head, and ſaluted on the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:180876:79"/>knee in mockery: who being by them thus dreſt in double purple, (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one was of his owne blood) torn with whips, &amp; pierced with thornes, he brings him forth to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> to moove them to compaſſion, hoping that a little blood would have contented them: but when no blood would pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but his heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blood, <hi>Pilate,</hi> like a falſe worldly Politician, thinking it better to yield to the death of one innocent, then to endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger a tumult, delivers <hi>Chriſt,</hi> againſt his owne
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:180876:80"/>conſcience, to be crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p>Concerning the time wherein our Saviour was crucyfied, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> there is a ſeeming difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two of the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts:</hi> for Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.14.</note> 
               <hi>It was about the ſixt houre when Pilate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him to be crucyfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Saint <hi>Marke</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 15.25.</note> 
               <hi>It was the third houre and they crucified him.</hi> To reconcile theſe two, we are to carrie with us, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> reckoned their Day by two ſort of houres, the one greater, the other the leſſe. The
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:180876:80"/>greater were called the houres of the Temple, and divided the Day into foure Quarters, whereof every one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained three houres a peece, which Quarters were reckoned under the name of the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, and fourth houre; for ſo many there were and no more; and then begun againe: on the Night, they are by <hi>David</hi> called the Night watches, as it ſeemes, where he ſayes, <hi>Mine eies prevent the Night watches.</hi> The leſſer houres, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckoned from one till
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:180876:81"/>twelve, after the manner that we doe, ſave that they begun not at the ſame time that ours do; for both their greater and leſſer houres, begun at ſixe a clocke with us, whether you beginne to reckon them at morning or evening: for the <hi>Iewes</hi> day begun at evening, as appeares both out of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and profane Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: ſo that begin to tell at ſixe in the evening, and twelve will end at ſixe in the morning, and beginne againe at ſixe in the morning, and your twelve wil end at 6 in the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:180876:81"/>evening, by our account. Which kind of recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was of Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, who ſayes in <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>The Evening and the Morning was the firſt day,</hi> beginning the day with the evening: and it is a more naturall kind of reckoning then ours which beginnes at midnight, both for day and night: for it begins when they beginne, and ends when they end, going orderly on with them both; ſo that the firſt houre when they began to worke was the firſt houre, the ſecond
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:180876:82"/>the ſecond, &amp;c. and ſo on in order: whereas the houre that we heare when we riſe, is ſixe or ſeaven, (for about that time men generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to worke) and therefore to us the firſt houre is not the firſt houre, but under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name. Theſe things will beſt be brought to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by a Table.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:180876:82"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="4">¶ The Greater houres, or houres of the Temple.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I</cell>
                     <cell>II</cell>
                     <cell>III</cell>
                     <cell>IIII</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="4">The Leſſer houres.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 2 3</cell>
                     <cell>4 5 6</cell>
                     <cell>7 8 9 </cell>
                     <cell>10 11 12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label" cols="4">Our houres as they agree with them both.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7 8 9</cell>
                     <cell>10 11 12</cell>
                     <cell>1 2 3</cell>
                     <cell>4 5 6</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>This figure ſhewes, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> firſt houre, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> both greater and leſſe, begun at ſixe, and ended
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:180876:83"/>in ſeaven; ſo that when our Dyall pointes at ſeaven, theirs pointed at one, ſhewing that the firſt houre was over, and the next begunne; when theirs pointed at two, ours at eight, and ſo on, till you come to twelve. In the greater houres, it muſt needes be otherwiſe; for their firſt greater houre was not ended, till our nine, which was their three, the next, not till their ſixe, which is our twelve; and then begunne the third houre which laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till our three in the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:180876:83"/>afternoone, as the fourth did alſo, which ended at our ſixe at night. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto this compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation do the Papiſts yet name their Canonicall houres:<note place="margin">The Third Houre.</note> for their <hi>Hora Tertiarum,</hi> is in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at nine, their ſixt is at noone, and their nine, at three a clocke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner, according to the account of the <hi>Iewes</hi> leſſer houres.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus explaned, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> there is no difficulty in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe names the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> give to the ſame houre: for they are but
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:180876:84"/>two names, ſignifying one thing; the one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckoning the ſame time by the greater houres, the other by the leſſe. For Saint <hi>Marke,</hi> who divides the day by the greater houres, he ſayes, it was the third houre, beginning by their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter houres; that is, ſixe a clocke newly over, by their leſſer houres; that is, full twelve, and paſt, with us, when our Lord was crucifyed. If any one object, This cannot be; for, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> had been crucifyed within the third greater houre, hee
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:180876:84"/>muſt not have beene ſo till one with us, for then in the Table, beginnes the third Quarter, or the third houre rather, in the greater houres: I anſwer, that one a clock, is all the ſpace betweene twelve and one, which houre is ended when one ſtrikes, and ſo the third houre beginnes at twelve newly over, which is the ſixt houre in the <hi>Iewes</hi> leſſer houres: and this hee will eaſily grant to be true, who conſiders, that the firſt houre that ever time meaſured, was not, or
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:180876:85"/>could not bee one, or the firſt houre, till an houre was runne, and then that might be called the firſt houre, or one, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and as that tooke his beginning with time, running on till it made a twelfth part of the day, and then tooke his name, according to his order: ſo muſt the third greater houre needes take his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at twelve, and end at his time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Now Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> on the other ſide, reckons not by the greater, but by the leſſer houres.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:180876:85"/>Therfore the beginning of the third greater houre with S. <hi>Marke,</hi> muſt needes be the ſixt leſſer houre with S <hi>Iohn;</hi> becauſe no ſooner this done, but that beginnes. And this the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> reckons from our Saviours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which muſt needes be a little before the third greater houre, in which hee was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed; for hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned a good prety while before he ſuffered; therefore it could not be ſo forward as S. <hi>Marke</hi> ſetts it, but within the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:180876:86"/>ſixt houre: yet, that is not full, or at leaſt but twelve with us, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was condemned: but before hee came to <hi>Golgotha,</hi> it could not but be paſt their ſixe, that is our twelve (at which time Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith hee was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) and ſo it muſt needes be the third houre, or quarter of the day, as Saint <hi>Marke</hi> reckons it, which to Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> was the ſixt houre.</p>
            <p>One thing more alſo wee may note out of the former figure: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> namely,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:180876:86"/>whence their error had his beginning, who thinke that our Saviour was crucifyed in the morning at nine, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not till three: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed, hee was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed at twelve, and ſo hanged but three houres upon the Croſſe; for hee was dead at the ninth houre, by the <hi>Iewes</hi> leſſer houres, which is our three in the afternoone. This error riſe, becauſe they thought <hi>Chriſt</hi> to have beene condemned at ſixe a clocke, by the <hi>Romane</hi> account, which is all one with ours, and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:180876:87"/>crucifyed at three, by the <hi>Iewes</hi> common reckoning in the little houres, which is our nine, and ſo they recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the times. But this opinion, (bee it ſpoken with reverence of their perſons) cannot ſtand; for Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes not of our, or the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> houres, but of thoſe which went for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon amongſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the ſtory of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſufferings, which were after the day was abroad, I meane his arraigning before <hi>Pilate,</hi> his whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, araying with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:180876:87"/>crowning with thorne, mocking, &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by the Soldiers, after he was examined: alſo his ſending to <hi>Herod,</hi> in the other ſide of the city, his ſtay there, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: againe, his ſecond triall, and finall condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation before <hi>Pilate:</hi> all theſe, and other I name not, could not poſſible be done, betwixt day and nine a clocke. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is hardly agreeable to reaſon, that our Lords Body ſhould bee ſixe houres together in paine ſo unſufferable, being of ſo feeling and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:180876:88"/>tender a compoſition: for though his Godhead could have upheld it, yet his humane nature had our infirmitie upon it;<note place="margin">See Mar. <hi>15.44.</hi> Where it is ſayd, Pilate marvailed he was dead ſo ſoone.</note> and therefore, hee is knowne to have <hi>ſhortned</hi> his time upon the Croſſe, at leaſt not to have held out till nature was ſpent, by his lowd cry upon the Croſſe, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he dyed not fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or through weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as other men do, who die becauſe nature can hould out no longer: therefore I reſt, yet, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them, who thinke his paſſion on the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:180876:88"/>Croſſe was but three houres long: the rather alſo, becauſe the death he ſuffered was ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, beeing upon the Croſſe, and his body na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, layd open to the ſcorne of all his enemies for our ſinnes, which might bee a principall cauſe why his paſſion was no longer.</p>
            <p>Many things there are to be obſerved in the time of our Saviours go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> and being upon the Croſſe. As firſt, the cruell uſage he had from the <hi>Iewes</hi> by the way, in that they made him car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:180876:89"/>his Croſſe till he fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: next, the womens teares that were ſhed for him, when hee went to his execution: upon that, the loving care he had to requite them, by letting them know their ſtate was more wofull, and fit to be bewayled then his. Therefore he bids them, <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem, weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelves.</hi> At his comming to the place of execution, <hi>Golgotha,</hi> or <hi>Calvary,</hi> that is, the place of a ſkull, their offering him wine min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with myrrhe, which
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:180876:89"/>was ſo ſowre and bitter, that one of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts calls it vineger min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with Gall, which hee refuſed: upon that, his crucifying betweene two theeves: <hi>Pilates</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle nayled above his head: his prayer for his enemies: the parting of his garments by the Souldiers: the reproches of them that ſtood by: the Blaſphemy of the unpenitent Theefe: the converſion of the other Theefe that repented: his laſt words to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his beloved Diſciple: the darkning
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:180876:90"/>of the body of the Sun, ere liee dyed, to whom it owed his light, as his Creator: his complaint to GOD that he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken him: his thirſt, his Iowd cry when, he gave up the Ghoſt, that it might appeare he dyed not of neceſſitie, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly layd downe his life, beeing in his full ſtrength, and having power to have retained it if hee would: his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending his Soule into his Fathers hands: and laſtly his death, after the CONSUMMATUM EST, that is, <hi>It is finiſhed,</hi> was pronounced, in which
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:180876:90"/>the worke of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption had his full period, ſo that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained no more either to doe or ſuffer.</p>
            <p>And now this Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is at an end: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> after which if you looke for a <hi>Plaudite,</hi> it wants not that neither, and ſuch a one alſo as is beſt fitting for ſo dreere a Story; for Saint <hi>Luke</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23 48</note> that <hi>All the people who ſawe this ſight, ſmote their breaſts,</hi> (which was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a Tragedy then clapping their hands) <hi>and returned.</hi> The uſe of theſe things in generall is this.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:180876:91"/>
            <p> To give us a ſight of our ſinnes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> which could not find pardon in the Sonne of GOD himſelfe, when hee ſtood in our perſon, though he bore them without ſinne.</p>
            <p>To teach us patience when we are called to ſuffer for them of deſert, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> by him that ſuffered for them undeſervedly, and yet never ſo much as once groned on the Croſſe, nor reviled or complained of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>To be thankfull unto GOD for the ſuffering of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> which hee hath
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:180876:91"/>appointed to be the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for their ſinnes that beleeve in him as their only Redeemer.</p>
            <p>To ſtirre us up to true ſorrow for ſinne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> and make us fly to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for remedy, that wee may be healed by his ſtripes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to ſerve him in newnes of life, till wee come to bee changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtate of incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble purity, never to ſinne any more: which eſtate, the merit of <hi>Chriſts</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by his ineſtimable value, hath bought for all, that truly ſeeke to, and ſerve him.</p>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:180876:92"/>
            <p> Many things more might be noted out of the things that fell out, either when, or after our Lord ſuffered: as, the darkning of the body of the Sunne, (for an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe it was not) becauſe the body of <hi>Truth</hi> even the <hi>Sunne of Righeouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> ſuffered: the renting of the vaile of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſignifying the abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of the Legall types or ſhaddowes; for the vayle was a figure of the Spirituall covering, which was before the eyes of the Church, till <hi>Chriſts</hi> comming: the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:180876:92"/>cleaving of the earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer the burden of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſuffering, and the weight of our ſinnes, making a way for them to deſcend to Hell, from whence they carne: the riſing of the Bodies of the Saints out of their graves, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the heart-ſtrings of death, which before bound them in their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, were braken by the death of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> laſtly, the buriall of the pure and untainted Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Holy Lord, and after his ſleepe in the grave for a time, his riſing againe in power,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:180876:93"/>to confound his enemies: all, yea every one of theſe might furniſh for a large diſcourſe. But my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was to ſpeake only of the paſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and thoſe things that belong to his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, rather then the things that are but acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall to them: as for the doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, it falls under another head, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to an affection of Ioy, not of Sorrow: of which two paſſions, the latter only is proper to this weeke; which here I would have ended, but
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:180876:93"/>that the weeke ends not with us till to morrow be done; ſomething ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for that I muſt find to ſay: which if it will not build, yet it may ſerve for filling, or Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh in thy building. Now reſt thee with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> untill the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thy Croſſe and Paſſion,</hi> Good Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:180876:94"/>
            <head>Meditations for SATURDAY</head>
            <p>WHere our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Paſſion takes an end, there ſhould ours beginne, for ſo muſt wee fulfill, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ſufferings, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the ſufferings of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Which though they were perfected when hee dyed, and needed no more, yet he will have us to caſt our <hi>mite</hi> into this <hi>Treaſary:</hi> Therefore, not becauſe
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:180876:94"/>hee needs wee ſhould ſorrow for him, let us take up our Croſſe this day, and follow him, but becauſe wee need to ſorrow for our ſelves, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> taught the Daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, this day, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is our Saviour ſleeping in his grave; in which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To whom our Land owes her firſt conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Councellour had as honorably laid him. Which action, though it hapned yeſter night, yet the effect of it reaches unto this day; in which our Saviours bodie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes the ſecret, which
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:180876:95"/>this worthy Councellor had beſtowed on him. In this buriall many things might bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that are worth the marking: As, 1 Holy <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> his courage, who durſt venter to offer to doe this, after hee had ſeene what had hapned to his Maſter: for this cauſe the Holy Ghoſt hath not left that part of his praiſe out of divine ſtory, to ſtirre up others by it;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.43.</note> for Saint <hi>Marke</hi> hath noted, that he went in boldly to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and craved the body of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> 2 That hee yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:180876:95"/>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> his owne roome, even the grave hee had digged for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.60</note> for Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> hath obſerved, that it was his owne Tombe in which <hi>Chriſt</hi> was laid. 3 That it was a new ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, in which never man had layen, as being fitteſt for that body-vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, or Maiden-corps, untoucht, and untaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 4 That it was in a Garden,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.41</note> hard by the place where <hi>Chriſt</hi> had beene crucified; that as man firſt fell in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſo out of a Garden he might, in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> bee
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:180876:96"/>raiſed up againe. 5 That there was no coſt awan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that could readily bee purchaſed; for <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> bought a fine lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.46.</note> and linnen in thoſe dayes, was not eath to come by; for they were not ſhirts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, as wee doe, which was the cauſe of their erecting Bathes in every towne, in which they waſhed ſo often: ſo that a hankerchiefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong, even the Romane riotors, was a rich to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as appeares out of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullus <hi>&amp;</hi> Veranius.</note> Poet. To helpe which coſt, bleſſed <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:180876:96"/>brought alſo an hundred pound weight of Mirrhe and Aloes, to enbalme him: and more would have beene done, but that it was evening, and ſpices then were not ready to bee bought. Out of theſe things, much might bee noted for this day, but that they were done the laſt Night, and ſo are not proper for this time.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing wee have on this day to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is the malice of the high Preiſts and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which ends not with the death of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:180876:97"/>our it is ſo cruell, but ſurvives, to ſhew it ſelfe againſt his dead body. Therefore they come to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Sir, we remember that that decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid, while hee was yet alive,</hi> AFTER THREE DAYES I WILL RISE A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAINE: <hi>Command therefore that the ſepulchre be made ſure untill the third day, leaſt his Diſciples come by Night, and ſteale him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and ſay unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, He is riſen from the dead: ſo the laſt error ſhall bee worſe then the firſt.</hi> Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which intreaty <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> anſwers them: <hi>Yee
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:180876:97"/>have a watch, goe your way, and make it as ſure as yee can:</hi> So they went and made the Sepulchre ſure, ſealing the ſtone, and ſetting a watch. S. <hi>Marke</hi> addes to this, that it was a great ſtone, which could not eaſily bee remooved, without ſtrength: and therefore when they come in the morning the women ſay, <hi>Who ſhall remoove us the Stone?</hi> So that now, ſure, <hi>Chriſts</hi> body is ſure enough: a great ſtone, and ſealed, and a watch by it, were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to keepe downe
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:180876:98"/>a dead body. But all this is to their greater ſhame; for it makes but the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our Saviours reſurrection the greater, which otherwiſe might have wanted witneſſes from his enemies: but now it hath even his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for witneſſe that hee roſe againe, (and that both to their coſt, and trouble,) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them. So let them watch this day as merrily as they will, to morrow will bee a heavy mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with them, come it aſſoone as it will, or can come, which to us is the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:180876:98"/>beginning of our joy.</p>
            <p>It is to us the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our joy, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but yet upon condition: that is, ſo wee bee right fitted to receive it. To fit thy ſelfe; firſt, thou muſt frame thy affection to the affection of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which they had for the want of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: For, Hee that had ſeene the cleaven, ſet ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together, or in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſhould no doubt, have ſeene ſo many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of heavines: and who had lookt as this day againe, on our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>Chriſts</hi> bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:180876:99"/>ſitting with the ſword thorough her heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.35.</note> which Saint <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> had fore-hight her, ſhould not have needed any other pourtraict to ſet forth the true paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Love, Hope, and Faith, under a cloud of ſorrow; for if any one wavered in doubt of <hi>Chriſts</hi> reſurrection, ſhee beleeved, becauſe ſhee knew him to bee GOD: and, on the other ſide, if any one mourned for his death, ſhee mourned the moſt, for ſhee was his Mother. Thus muſt thou do to; <hi>Mourne;</hi> but
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:180876:99"/>for thy ſinnes, that cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed <hi>Chriſt:</hi> yea thou muſt ſet thy ſelfe among his Murderers, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſets thee, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.23.36.</note> 
               <hi>I am one of thoſe,</hi> LORD, <hi>that crucifyed thee:</hi> Stand here faſt now, for this is the ſafeſt place for thee at firſt; for thou muſt come to joy through this kind of ſorrow, or elſe in <hi>Chriſt</hi> thou canſt not have it.</p>
            <p>Next to this, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> thou muſt learne of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women that waited for <hi>Chriſts</hi> reſurrection, how to waite for his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againe in thy heart;
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:180876:100"/>for they waited with their ſweete odours, and ſo muſt thou do too. What theſe odours are, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> tells thee in his Revelation, where hee ſayes, <hi>The odours that are offered in heaven, are the prayers of the Saints:</hi> Now thou muſt be as holy, that is, as Saint-like as thou canſt; therefore thou muſt not want thy odours, ſuch as thou canſt get: which if they bee not for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balming, as the womens were, but for burning, it is the better; for it was a fault of love in them, to
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:180876:100"/>provide that <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body ſhould not ſee corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Pray thou then, and let the heate of zeale ſend out thy ſighes, and thy ſervent devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in a ſmoake up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven: thus ſhalt thou cenſe thy ſoule. that <hi>Chriſt</hi> may come the next day to thee, and thou maiſt bee received of him at his Table.</p>
            <p>And now I have brought thee where I would leave thee; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> even upon thy knees, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed art thou when hee
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:180876:101"/>comes, if hee finde thee ſo doing. For as he roſe, that thou mightſt riſe; ſo from that place, if from any, he will raiſe thee up, yea lend thee his hand to ſet thee on thy feete, that thou maiſt ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him for ever. Waite thus then, and powre out thy prayers unto GOD, to prepare thee for his comming: and if thou remember others in thy prayers, (as thou art bound to the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of heaven in them, which runnes upon OUR, and VS) put mee in among them, (yet of
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:180876:101"/>neede I beg it rather then deſert) and I have a better reward of my paines from thee, then I can looke for. Now I muſt leave thee: for I know thou wilt ſhut thy doore when thou pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> bids thee.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.6.</note>
            </p>
            <closer>SO GOD SPEEDE THEE.</closer>
            <trailer>Tu autem DOMINE Miſerere Noſtri.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:180876:102"/>
            <l>THe love that <hi>LOVE</hi> had laſt to ſhew,</l>
            <l>The life that <hi>LIFE</hi> had laſt to ſpend,</l>
            <l>The paines unto Gods juſtice due,</l>
            <l>Suffer'd by God in manhood true,</l>
            <l>The price which bought us God to Friend,</l>
            <l>The tree on which ſalvation grew,</l>
            <l>The merit which ſhall never end,</l>
            <l>But doth to infinite extend,</l>
            <l>In one weeke, though the dayes be few,</l>
            <l>This booke would ſeeme to comprehend,</l>
            <l>Thinke you it can? Yet if it hath not wonne it,</l>
            <l>Reade but your Chriſts-Croſſe, and there God hath done it.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
